*  First Reactions to ChatGPT Plugins
*  Q&A: Keeping up with AI
*  Q&A: ChatGPT Intepreter changes Programming
*  Q&A: ChatGPT for Education
*  Q&A: GPT4 Sketch to Website Demo
*  Q&A: AI Competition and Human Jobs
*  ChatGPT Plugins as App Store
*  Google vs ChatGPT
*  Nader Dabit on Selling His GPT App
*  Q&A: ChatGPT Waitlist and Voice
*  LangChain with Human in the Loop
*  Google vs Microsoft vs Apple
*  ChatGPT Plugin Ideas
*  Not an app store?
*  LangChain and the Future of AI
*  Q&A: ChatGPT Bots and Cronjobs
*  Logan Joins Us!
*  Q&A: Plugins Rollout
*  Q&A: Plugins Discovery
*  Q&A: OpenAI vs BingChat
*  Q&A: App Store Monetization
*  Q&A: ChatGPT Plugins API
*  Q&A: Python Interpreter
*  The History of App Stores and Marketplaces
*  LindyAI's Flo Crivello Joins Us
*  AI Safety
*  Multimodal GPT4
*  Designing AI-safe APIs
*  Flo's Closing Comments
Hello and welcome to the Latent Space Emergency episode. This is our first ever where chatty PT just dropped a plugin ecosystem today, or at least they demoed their plugins. It's still on the wait list, but it is the app store moment for ai. And we did an emergency two hour space with Logan from OpenAI and Flo Coveo from Lin AI and a bunch of our friends.
And if you ever wanted to listen to what it's like to hear developers process in real time when a new launch happens, this is it. Enjoy,
First Reactions to ChatGPT Plugins
I assume everyone has read the blog post. For me the, the big shit was do you see Greg Brockman's tweet about FFMPEG? I did not. I should check it out. It is amazing. Okay, so. So ChatGPT can generate Python code. We knew this, this is not new, and they can now run the code that it generates.
This is not new. I mean this is like, this is good. It's not like surprising. It's, it's fine. It can run FFMPEG code. You can upload a file, ask it to edit the video file, and it can process the video file and then it can give you the link to download the video file. So it's a general purpose compute platform.
Wow. Did they show how to do this? Agents? I just, I just, I just pinned it. I just, it did I, did I turn into this space? I dunno how to use it. Yeah, it's, it's showing up there. Okay. It can run like is. Is, is, is my And by, by the way hi to people. I, I don't know how to run spaces. I, I not something I normally do.
But You wanna say something? Please request. But yeah, reactions have a look at this video because it run, it generates and runs video editing code. You can upload any arbitrary file. It seems to have good enough compute and memory and file storage. This is not chat anymore, man. I don't know what the hell this is.
What, what is this?
Well, progress has been all faster than I expected. . That's all I can, I, I, I don't know how to respond. . Yeah. It's pretty wild. I wonder, I wonder, I'm wondering how, how this will affect, like opening up the app store different from, let's say Apple App Store when it opened up. Because there are a lot of, of big companies just building stuff already and how like a small developer will be able to, to build something that's not already there.
I dunno. It will be interesting. So one thing that's really nice, have you seen the installation process for the plugins? It's right at the bottom of the blog post and you have to play the video to kind of see it, but literally anybody can write your own plugin. It's a small little json file. It's, it's literally like 10 lines of code.
It's 10 nights of, you described what your plugin does in English, you given an open API spec. That's it. That, that's, that's the plugin. It's amazing. You can distribute your plugin. This is, this is, this is easier than extensions manifest v3, which nobody knows how to use. This is English.
You write English . So, so, yeah. I mean I think, I think I think there'll be a lot of people trying to develop for this if they can get access, which you know, everybody's on a wait list. I, I've, I've signed up to 200 wait lists this week. . I wonder if, if it'll be different if you, if you sign up as a, as a developer or as the chat user.
Hopefully it doesn't matter, right? Use different emails and sign up to both. Let's, let's just see, in fact, use t to generate like, plausible sounding reasons for why you want to build whatever. Cause they don.
But yeah, I mean, how do you compete? I, I don't know, man. You know, it, it's really OpenAI is definitely a partnership strategy to do what they do here which means they're essentially picking favorites. So if you're a competitor of Expedia Kayak Open Table Wolf from Zapier, you're a shit out of luck, kind of, you know?
Cause these are presumptive winners of their spaces. Right. And it'll happen in too many industries, probably. Right. I was thinking about maybe summarization or, or I don't know, YouTube video summarization, but there seems to be some application of that already on the examples that you shared. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
They have shared that, but I think there's always room to improve the experience. It's just, you know It's interesting which platform, like sort of platform strategy, right? Like if you write an OpenAI chat plugin, you instantly gain access to a hundred million users, right? All of them can instantly use your thing.
Whereas if you are a standalone app or company, good luck trying to able to use OpenAI through you. There's just no point. So you much rather just be on OpenAI platform and promote there. The the fortunate thing is they don't have some kind of like popularity ranking yet. Actually, someone should go open, someone should do register, like OpenAI plugins list.com or something where like everyone can like submit their own opening app plugins and like upload them, review them cuz this like, this is not a complete app store without reviews and a rating system and a reputation system and probably monetization opening app probably doesn't care about that.
But I mean, I can go start that right now. Fuck. I can go start it right now.
Yeah, it'll, it'll take a while, right? Like this is the, like the basic version of the, of the app evolving. But this is a pretty basic version. Yeah. The basic version can browse the web, it can write, write an execute code. It can retrieve you know, we can retrieve data from documents, right? So all the documents search just died.
There's like five of these in Y Combinator right now. Oh.
Examples. Pretty crazy how, how they use the FFMPEG library or, I dunno if I'm saying that correctly, but right in there. You don't need to, to write code to,
it's crazy. Dunno. Yeah. Any reactions? Please, please, you know, open space. Anyone can request a speaker. Oh, Ash, come on in. Ash. I have to add you a speaker. Yeah, we're, we're just reacting here. I just, I, I needed a place to talk and I'm in Japan and I don't have anyone else to talk to, so I need, I, I I just want to share this moment.
I think it's a special moment in history. This is the biggest new app source since ever. Yeah. Hey, Shawn. I think plugin is already taken. . Oh man. Someone, someone bought it already. Yep. , of course. Right? Of course. , what are your reactions? What how are you feeling? What's what are you seeing out there?
Just crowdsource all the tweeting. Yeah, man, it's, it's been wild. I mean, I get out of there to like five minutes and then anything drops, you know, , I think productivity today will be like zero. If I, if I still, like, I quit my job you know, a few weeks ago but I would not be working today. There, there's no point.
There's nothing else. There's nothing else that's important, like, nothing's going on. Like this is the only story. Yep. . I wonder if you have any, any frameworks or anyone that's listening any frameworks on, on how you're handling all of this new, new stuff. Like every single day if something new comes up and, or you can like get the, the wait list invitations to, to use the new products.
Q&A: Keeping up with AI
Like, for example, today I just got the, the one from GIK cli and I was just playing around with that. And then suddenly I started to see all of the, these Twitter threads with announcements. It's getting crazy just to follow up with, with the stuff. And every day something new comes up and started. I was starting to feel a lot of formal, you know, like, h how do you keep up with all of these?
Or how do you focus? Does anyone have any, any good frameworks for that? Well, feel free to respond. Also, we, we have some more room if anyone wants to share your feelings. This is a, this is a safe space to share your feelings because. We all dunno how to react right now. I don't know. I just, I, I, I have a few notifications on for OpenAI employees and people that I do that I think do good recaps.
So in other words, find the people who are high signal and who do a lot of gathering of other people's stuff for, and then just subscribe to those people and trust that that is 90% of it and forget the 10%
Alright. And Sean probably, I have, I have another question. So I can't really figure out like what's left for us to do, you know, without AI tools. Like what, what is we learn next? You know, there's no learning some coding stuff, because you can only do that. You know, we can't do arts, we can't do poetry.
Farming
bakery, probably making things with your hands. Enjoying the sun.
Do you guys think this should be regulated? Like you don't go more than like the speed is going? I don't know. I dunno. There's, there's no point. Like if, like, if you regulate OpenAI, then someone else will come along. The secret is out now that you can't do this, and at most you'll slow things down by 10 years.
You called the secret. This is the end. . Yeah. Yeah. I, I don't know. Secret is out. China's trying to do it right, so I don't know if people have seen, but like China was, was fairly strict on crypto, which is probably good for them. And now they're, they're also trying to clamp down on AI stuff, which is funny because oa like they're, you know, the m i t of of China Ihu, I was actually doing like producing like really good bilingual models.
But yeah, they, they seem to be locking this down, so we'll see. We'll see. Right? Like you know, in, in, in sort of the, the free world there, there's open innovation that may be unsafe. OpenAI, try to be safe. You know, there, there's a big part of the blog post that was talk, talking about red team meeting and all that.
I'm sure every one of us skipped it. I skipped it. And then and then we just care about capabilities and now that, you know, every time people have their minds opened, like, I did not know Ron. EG in chat.
Q&A: ChatGPT Intepreter changes Programming
Now that I know my conception of what a REPL is, or literate programming or what a notebook is, is completely blown outta the water, right?
Like there's no like this, this is a new form factor for me. So not now that I know that I won't be innovating on that or trying to, to shape this into something that I can use because I want to use this, and this is, this is clearly better. Does, does this ha have to do with, with the, like AI as backend?
Yeah. Ideas that have been, yeah. You know, GP as backend. So, so apparently I had a few friends reach out to those guys and they're not doing that because it's not mature enough. Like it works for a simple demo. So, so for, for those who don't know ScaleAI did a hackathon I think two months ago just before I did mine.
And the winner on the hackathon was, was something called GPT is all you need for backend. And they actually what in register? DBC is backend.com. But as far as I can tell, they're not gonna start a company based on that because if you even push a little bit, it falls apart, right? So GPT3 wasn't good enough for that.
Maybe GPT4 is maybe GPT5, but then it'll still be super slow and super expensive. Like you don't want to run, you know, a large language model on every API request. So I don't know. I think it'll be good for scaffolding. I think it'll be good for re type use cases. Like, Hey, I need to edit this video on an ad hoc basis.
I don't, I don't want to learn FFMPEG. I don't need to now, because I can just talk to ChatGPT. That makes sense. But if you want a reliable, scalable backend you probably don't want to use it on a large language model, but that's okay because language model can probably help you write it rather than run it.
Hey, Lessio. Hey guys. Oh yeah. Hey guys. What's up? Hey, yeah, we're, we're just, there's no structure. Just drop your reactions. Let's go. Awesome. Awesome, awesome guys.
Q&A: ChatGPT for Education
What do you think what if Shawn, what do you think if you could use you know AI and the education field, like, you know, like personal attribution system for students?
What's the thought automation education or attribution edu edu education. Yeah. That is the holy grail. This is called the Blooms two Sigma problem. Like the, the, the, one of the big issues of education is we have to teach to the slowest person in the class. And, and, you know, I'm a beneficiary of, of a gifted education system where they take out you know, nominally high IQ people and put them in a separate class.
And, and yeah, we did, we did do better. What if we can personalize every student's experience there's, there's some educational theory. This is called Bloom's two Sigma problem. Where the results will be better. I think that we are closer, but like, I still hope that we're pretty far , which sounds like a negative, like why do I want to deny education to students?
Because if we are there, then we will have achieved theory of mind for ai. The AI has a very good model, is able to develop a representation of who you are, is able to develop theories that the test who you are in, in a short amount of time. And I, it's a very dangerous path to, to go down. So I want, I want us to go slowly rather than fast on, on the education front.
Does that make sense? Yeah, definitely. It makes a lot sense and yeah, definitely. I think personally the education for each student and making it turn the best way would be great. And what do you think how about like, first of all, I'm, I'm having very curious, curious question, you know, like we are having, this week was full of launches, so how you guys are keeping up with if we're not, this is, I created the space though cuz I cannot handle it.
Today, today was my breaking point. I was like I don't know what's happening anymore. Yeah, like every single day I'm just in constant anxiety that like everything I assumed about the world is gonna be thrown up. Like I don't know how to handle it. This is a therapy session, so feel free to express.
Definitely. It's, it's been a very overwhelming feeling for everyone of us like that. I think, you know, like past two weeks and like the industry was definitely a lot, lot of ones we are definitely open for, you know, to discuss more about it. Thanks a lot for this space. Sean. Yeah. Appreciate. Yeah. Va one more thing.
So I think that the most constrained version of education use cases is language teaching. So there are a few language teachers out there speak I think is one of them that is an OpenAI partner. And they're also part of the chat GPT plugin release. , but there are also other language tutor platforms.
You can certainly have your news. There was one that was released maybe like four or five months ago that you can try to see what the experience is like. And you can, you can tell when the teacher has no idea who you are and it breaks the illusion that you're speaking to another human. So I, I just, you can experience that today and, and decipher yourself if we're ready for that.
I hope that we're not ready and it seems like we're not ready. Yeah, definitely, definitely. Thanks a lot for sharing. And guys, what do you think?
Q&A: GPT4 Sketch to Website Demo
Like I, in the launch of four we have show that we could, you know, generate apps and web apps just from you know, like a single simple sketch, you know different tent.
Just start from sketch. So what do you think like how, how it would be impacting the industry? It's all because it's not just like that, that sketch was very, was a very shitty sketch. Right. It was just like drawn on a piece of paper. But if you combine that with the multimodal, like it was that they had another part of that demo where they had a screenshot of the discord the opening eye discord and you're mm-hmm.
and they put it in and it, it like read the entire screen to you and if you can read the entire screen, you can code the entire . Screen. So it's over like
It's definitely, I think interaction, interaction designers, you know, like people who like, think design function still have some time. Yeah. I, I just, I just, I just tried the same thing, you know on bar today and it was like much more better than GPT3 so definitely it's you know, things are really changing.
Q&A: AI Competition and Human Jobs
Great forward. I'm, I'm really worried what we wanna do, you know? Do you think the competition will like stable everything? Like what competition? Anthropic. Well, like Google, Google won't race, I don't think. Google Race, like Google the fight. The one that, the one that launched the W links list of blog posts.
That, that Google.
Well, no, not, not the list. Not the list. Competitions will come. . I have a question. I mean I mean my fear is many of the jobs that are going away, whether it is developer and designers, because I mean, I think GPT four is very capable. So how to deal with it. I mean, it's going to replace, I mean, many of the jobs, that's for sure.
Yeah. It's okay. We'll find new jobs or we'll, we'll not need jobs anymore. We should, we should also, Start universal basic income. That's, that, that is something I, I do believe, yeah, I think the, the main change is going from the web of like, syntax to like the web of Symantec. So if your job is valuable because, you know, a unique syntax or like, you know, how to transform things from like words to syntax, I think that will be a lot less useful going forward.
But the Symantec piece is still important. So a lot of product work, it's not just writing CSS and HTML and like the backend for it. It's a lot more than that. So I just thinking about how do you change your skills to do that. But yeah, even the sketch, you know, you gotta like, you gotta draw the sketch and to draw the sketch, you gotta know where the button should go.
You know, you have, you know, incorrect with it. Yeah. I'm just processing this as I, I just read the whole thing as well. And Yeah, I mean, it's been a wild wild couple of weeks and it's gotten me thinking that maybe all our role was over the past couple years was we were just middlemen to talk to computers, right?
So we're sitting in between, it's over man PMs or business folks or whoever wanna build a product. And then as a software developer, you're just a middle manish talking to the machine and it seems like. N LP is the way forward and, oh, yeah. Yeah. It's, it's been it's been, it's been a while.
ChatGPT Plugins as App Store
Couple of weeks. It's, I feel like we all just have to move either move upstream or, or find other jobs. You just gotta move upstream, either toward product directly. Cuz right now the plugin is yeah, is, is just you know, it's still a very sanitized UI that is controlled by OpenAI. But imagine them opening up the ui portion as well.
So you no longer need to have a siloed product that needs to integrate. ChatGPT instead you can bring your product directly into into ChatGPT, I don't think exactly. I think that would be probably the next next logical move after this, and I'm sure they're already thinking about that.
So that's a great, I don't know if this is, it's wild. What are you guys think? Yeah. Yeah. Like, so before you came up, right, I was, I was talking about this like ChatGPT has at least a hundred million users. Why would you bring people to your platform rather than write a plugin for ChatGPT and use their platform?
It's an open question now. Zapier just launched their integration. OpenAI and OpenAI just launched their integration of Zapier. Which one is gonna be more interesting? Probably OpenAI.
Totally a hundred percent . this is the app store of wow, our century of our decade. Like, I don't know, maybe century. I, I think the thing with ster though, if you think about it, like how many native apps do you download every week, every month versus like how many web things you use. So I think it's all about whether or not long-term opening eyes incentivize to keep broadening the things you can do within the plugin space.
And I think the lab, you know, as this technology gets more widespread, they're gonna have a lot more pressure from regulators, safety, blah, blah, blah. So I'm really curious to see you know, all, all the, all the government stuff that they'll, they'll have a congressional on this in six months and by then it will be completely irrelevant.
It's like that beside that time, they, they, they called it the GameStop guy after he made like 20 million on GameStop. And he just, you know, he was like, yeah, you know, followed the rules, made a bunch of money for those who don't know, unless you're our co-host. On the, we were supposed to drop an episode today, which I was supposed to work on, and then Chatty Phi dropped this thing, and now I, I can't think about anything else.
So this, this is my excuse for not, for for not working on the podcast today. . I know it's funny, we have like three, four recorded ones and spend last week, like GP four came out and we're like, okay, everybody's talking about this is irrelevant. What else? Anything else? Like, but I'm really excited about the, I, I feel like the first, the first use case for this, and I think he tweeted it about it too, is like, before if you had to do like data reformatting and stuff like that, it was really hard to do programmatically.
You know, like you didn't have an natural language interface and now you have it. And before if you had to integrate things together, like you could explain it very easily, but you couldn't like, put the APIs together and now they kind of remove all that part. So I'm excited to see what this looks like.
For commercial use cases, you know, you could see like, is there gonna be like a collaborative ChatGPT where like you're gonna have two, three people in the same conversation working on things. I think there's a lot of ui things that will improve. And so as we have lining from OpenAI for a second, almost pulled them up, but I'm sure you cannot talk about it
But yeah, it'll be interesting to see. Yes, sir. We're extremely excited. Extremely excited. I, I don't, if you, I don't know what else I'm, I'm like, so as far as I can tell there's the, there's hacker and Twitter. I haven't looked at Reddit yet, but I'm sure there's a bunch of reactions on Reddit.
I'm sure there's the OpenAI discord that we can also check out. I got locked out of the discord at some point, but yeah, anyone, anyone else like see news, demos, tweets the whole point of this is that it's live, so please feel free to share on comments or anything like that. But yeah. Yeah, the, the craziest thing I saw was the Mitchell from Hash.
We tweeted about Yes. How the integrations actually work and you just write a open APIs back and then just use natural language to describe what it's supposed to do. And then their model does everything. I wonder if they're using the off-the-shelf model or they have like a fine tune model to actually run integrations.
I wonder, I don't think they'll ever say it. Knowing them, probably they would just use the base one cuz they want, like, I think opening eyes kind of wants a God model, right? There's no point. It's not intellectually interesting to do small models, but like, like it's trivial. Yeah. Yeah. It's, this is a minor optimization problem as far as the, the long arc of history and the, the point is to build a gi safe agi and I, I do think this is kind of safe, right?
Like, . One of the criticisms that people were saying on hacks was that this is very closed. Like it's, it is an app store. At any point opening, I can randomly decide to close this like they did for Codex, and then they change their minds. Whereas if you use something like Alan Chain, it is more open and something that at the same time, like clearly this is a better integration path than long-chain.
Like, I much rather write this kind of plugin than a long-chain plugin. So they, they've managed to, I mean, they know how to ship man, like they're an AI research lab, but they also know how to ship product. Mm-hmm. . Yeah. I, I'm curious to see what the pricing models gonna look like. Also, I mean, if I'm writing the plugin, this is great because I don't even have to take care of the compute, you know, like, I just plug it in, then they actually run everything for me.
Yeah, but how, how it'll be monetized. I mean if the is giving their plugin know Expedia, I mean, people will not go to their website. Yeah. I don't, I mean, yeah. I have no idea that they, I don't think they said also don't super care . Yeah. It's because in the, in the app store, it's transaction driven.
But on Channel G, you're just paying a flat fee every month. So like, you can't really do revenue share on a flat fee. And I don't think that we use like, the Spotify model, but it's like a why not the amount of times? No, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait. Why not , you have Spotify. I just, Spotify model works. Cause swyx has power, right?
Opening has power. Same thing. They have all the audience. Yeah. But every, every every song is like the same value. Like if you listen to song actor to song y. , like, you're gonna make the same money. Like if I'm calling the API to, for like the meme generator or if I'm calling the API for the, you know, business summary thing, they're probably gonna cost the firm things, you know, so it's kind of hard to model up for OpenAI to say, Hey, okay, we're charging, we're going from 20 to 35 bucks a month.
But then like, how do you actually do royalties on a per model basis? Like how do people decide what royalties to negotiate? This probably needs to be a flat fee, but I dunno. Or put your credit card it OpenAI and then every time you wanna use a plugin, you pay for it separately. Uvp, usage based pricing all the way, and then you just get at the end of every month.
Exactly the, the only question mark is like, how much does OpenAI value the training they on and like how much they wanna subsidize the usage. Canada they have, they have promised to not use any of our usage data for training. So, oh, but the, I think like the plugins, it's a, it's a different thing.
It's like, like how you could, you could easily see how are like requests usually structure for like these things, you know, like, are people searching? So how are people searching for flights and stuff like that. I don't know. I haven't read the terms for like the actual plugin, you know, so. Well if anyone has please come up to speak cuz we're all processing this live.
This is the therapy session. Yeah, go ahead. One thing I see is basically you have to change the plugin I mean, to ask anything or even if you did browsing, right? I mean I see. I mean, they are becoming directly competitor to Microsoft also, I think, because now a user can actually just see, I mean, instead of being chat or Google, I mean they, they just.
Basically select the browsing plugin and basically get all the updated data. And other thing I see is basically you have to change the plugins. Like if you want to use the Expedia data, I don't know how it'll fit with the browsing plugin or you can select multiple plugins. But yeah, it is interesting.
I mean, if we get access, yeah, there is no actual browsing plugin. The browsing is a new model. So just like you can select GT three, GT 3 45, GT four, there's a new model now that says browsing alpha. So you, you can use CHATT in browsing mode and then you can use it in plugins mode, which which is a different model again.
So the, the plug browsing don't cross over.
Oh, that's interesting. And how do you see, I mean, in this whole descending, they are becoming competitive to Microsoft or how they're playing it out. I mean, Bing is just by the way, like, yeah, this, this killed the bing wait list. Cuz you don't need to wait for Bing. You can just use the browser mode open of Chatt.
How does it compete? It competes for sure. I don't think Microsoft cares. I don't think OpenAI cares. This is one of those things where like, you know, they are the two, two friends, you know, and they're clearly winning, so who cares? I don't like, I don't imagine it takes any of their mental bandwidth at all.
Yeah. The main thing is Google is Yeah, the main, like how is Google competing? Well let's see. Right. Bard is out there. I haven't got us yet, but could be interesting. Again, like it doesn't seem like they have the shipping capacity or velocity of Open I Microsoft and. That is probably going to bite them eventually because there's already been a big brain drain.
Something like four researchers, four, the top Google Brain researchers left Google Brain for OpenAI in January. And you know, those are the ones that I know about. And I, I imagine there's, there's quite a bit of brain, brain drain and firing going on at Google, so who knows.
All right, well, any other topics, concerns? Hyperventilation, if you just wanna scream I can turn down the volume and you can just, ah, for like five minutes. , that was literally, I was like, I, I need to like scream and just, ah, because what is going on?
I said that I'm filling out the form right now for the Oh, yeah. Okay. So wait list. So use use chat t to fill out that form. Right. And then, and then use a fake, use a different email and fill out the form a different way. This maximizes . I'm going to ask GT for what plugin do I want to build or, right, right.
Exactly. Yeah. Yeah. I, we can brainstorm. My plugins can live. Yeah. I think that will be a fun exercise. Like the, the main thing that breaks my brain is just this, this whole ability to run code, right? Like this is a new notebook, a new ripple. Mm-hmm. It, it looks like it has storage and it has memory.
Probably it has GPUs. That, I mean, can we run Lama inside GP?
I don't know if that's a, a model within a model. I think for me, most of the things come to like, you know, if I have my own personal assistant, what I want the assistant to do. I think like travel is like the first thing that comes to mind. Like, if I could use pt Yeah. Expedia, plug in with my calendar.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. But it needs to like know where I, where I'm supposed to be going to, you know, like if I just add a calendar that's like I'm going to, you know, room this week. Yeah. And then like can automatically both send my calendar and say, okay, these are like, or like the times that you like to travel, I know that you don't like ops and yada yada, yada.
That's one thing that I've always, we had this thesis at my peers firm about personalized consumer. There's so many website like, . I go to a lot of basketball games and every time I open Ticketmaster or whatever, it always shows me that she's a seat. And like, I'm not gonna see, that's not what I, that's not the tickets I wanna buy, you know?
But doesn't matter how many tickets I buy, never remembers that. So I think a way to say, to see, take all the information in and suggest, Hey, I saw that there's actually a price drop for the specific seats that you want, not for like any seats. You know, I think that would be a, a very good use case. So I've been a personal entertainment assistant for like, travel like going to shows, going to games.
That would be cool. That's what I'll submit on the wait list. Then we'll see if anybody cares. Right. Did you see get Lindy? Yeah. Yeah. At the, maybe you wanna recap, get Lindy for people. I'm gonna pin it up on the. . Yeah. So basically and this is like the kind of like a assistant lend the ai, right?
Yeah. Lend the ai it's on the board right now. Yeah. For those who can see it through the space. Yeah. Yeah. Actually at the AI Thinkers meet up the, the other day, you can basically like create all kind of like personal workflows and you, it kind of looks like integrations like zier, but it's actually just natural language.
So you can pop this thing up on your desktop and say, trying to hire 10 software engineers. So go on LinkedIn and plan 10 software engineers. The next step, draft a, an email that says, I'm the CEO of this company and I'm trying to hire for my team. If you wanna talk. Then the next step is like, send emails to all these people and it's gonna use people data labs or something else that they use on the backend to get the emails.
Then it actually sends the emails and. This is just gonna run in the background as if it was like you actually doing it. It's pretty neat that you don't have to write the actual integrations. Like it just uses natural language so you're not bound by what they build. Like theoretically anything you wanna integrate with, you can just explain to it how it works and it's gonna figure out how to do it.
So there's a wait list now. Flow didn't give us any papers just because we were at the meetup, so I'm also waiting to get access to it, but it looks really, really good. Yeah, so generative AI's top use case is generating wait lists, right? Like we we're, we are, so we have never had such an easy way to generate a lot of wait lists.
A lot of signup for witness. Oh my God. So much interest. So much product market fit. But also you know, one thing that you, you raising this point? I think, I think, I think by the way, I also pin this up. Mindy can support complex roles like no meetings on Fridays, all one-on-ones on Monday. , I like my meetings back to back within five minutes.
Five minutes in between. So it's just arbitrary rules that you could not program in a normal assistant type environment without a large language model. Which is kind of exactly what you want when you're booking your travel, right? Like, hey, I only like aisle seats unless it's it's a flight that is less than one hour that I don't care, right?
Mm-hmm. . So stuff like that I think is, is super interesting. And but also like not a common use case. Like how many times do you travel a year? Like, you know, five, right? Like more than that, but yes, I think for, yeah, a lot of times it's not a, it's not like a super widespread thing, especially if you don't do it or work.
If it's infrequent, you want high value and then if it's, if it's frequents, you can do low value, right? Like that, that's the sort of binary tradeoff, like the Uber is sort of frequent and low value. Airbnb is high value in frequent there's something of that nature. . So like, you want, you want sort of inspections of that sort.
Google vs ChatGPT
But the other thing that you brought to my attention was, and, and has room for Google to do something is do you notice that OpenAI plugins, none of them are Google because they're not friends. So Open BT will probably never have first party access to Google Calendar, probably never your Gmail and probably whatever, you know, Google copies, OpenAI again.
They will do, Hey, we have all your docs.
Yeah, I, I, I'm interested in that because I don't know if you remember, but like in the first iPhone, like YouTube came, like pre-installed on the homepage and then I forgot when, but one of the early ioss, they removed it. So now obviously Google's not a friend. Who's gonna be a friend in the future, who's not gonna be like, do we all have to hail our AI overlords?
Yeah. To get access to the, the only plugin system. Yeah. The only winners are brown CEOs. Think you're fine. Alright. But yeah, yeah. I just invited nada. C my old boss. Hi. You can't lurk. I, I want, I want to hear from you. And but, but also, you know, yeah, I, I think the Google point is actually novel.
I'll probably write something about that. Yeah. I mean, I'll have to write something about this today. So please feed me things to write.
Nader Dabit on Selling His GPT App
Oh, there we go. Hey, what's up man? What are you think. I know it's like, not entirely your space, but like you're, you're all about the future, right? I mean I did build and sell an AI company about a month ago, . I did the wait, what travel app was built on GP T three Tweeted about You sold it? Yeah.
It was getting like a hundred thousand visitors a day, like 60 to 80,000 unique a day. And then I, whoa. Yeah, I sold it like within about 24 hours. I tweeted out that it was for sale. I had like 30 or 40 people in my inbox. Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa. Okay. I need, so like, but you're right. This isn't my, my man like domain of expertise.
It's fine. You make, you may just a thousand dollars on the side. It's, it's cool. Wait, wait. So I saw you tweet your original thing, which was, Hey you know, GP three can plan your travel. I don't know what happened since then. Can you, can you fill the rest of. Yeah. Yeah. So I mean I was basically, you know, I travel a lot for work.
I, I do travel like once a month and, you know, but I'm also very resource constrained on my time. So I usually like to spend like one day sightseeing. So what I typically do is I go a trip advisor and then I kind of like, you know, Google around and like look at all these things and it usually takes me about an hour to figure out like what I wanna do on my day or two off to go, like sighting.
And then I realized GPT3, you know, you can just literally ask and, and say, okay, within X number of. Like, I'm gonna be in this city, I want to have an iter itinerary. You know, you can give all these different parameters and it gives back a really good response. This was before GPT, even three and a half or four was out.
So I just built like a nice UI on top. Then, like I mapped over the results and, and was linking to, you know, the the Google searches for these different items and, and kind of made it into a nice user interface and, you know, just built it out and tweeted it out. And it, it just got a lot of traction and attention.
Like I said, I had around a hundred thousand visitors a day, like right off the bat, 60,000 uniques like per day. So it was getting a shitload of of traction and. I don't have a lot of free time to kind of like, maintain or build something like that out. So it was costing me money, but I wasn't monetizing it.
So the way that I was thinking to monetize it would be to use affiliate links and stuff like that. So I could either, you know, spend time figuring out a way to monetize it or just try to make, flip it and just make some money. So I decided to sell it and that was kind of it. I just sent a tweet out and kind of said, this is for sale, who wants it?
And I had I had so much inbound from that that I had to delete the tweet within about two hours cuz I was just unable to keep up with all the people that were coming in. And I filled it out a couple of offers and I, I found the person with the most money that could close within the shortest amount of time and just took it.
Well done. Well done. Nice. Awesome. I need a, I need a, I need an applause button right here. . Okay. So with that context your thoughts on today, what you seeing? There's Expedia there, but. Comment on travel or not travel, whatever you want. . Yeah, I'm still reading up on the, the chat plugins actually.
And I was hoping to kind of chime into this to learn a little more about how they work. I'm here on the the page. I've had API access from fairly early on. I signed up and I've been you using it a lot. I'm trying to find some different ways to integrate AI and machine learning into the blockchain space.
There's a lot of stuff around civil resistance that I think are gonna be, you know, pretty interesting use cases for us. It's obviously not like a, a a type of use case that is gonna be useful to, to the general public maybe, but yeah, I'm still, actually still trying to understand how these plugins work.
So what have you seen the developer documentation, which developer documentation at the bottom? Yes. That's where I'm, I'm check, I'm reading through as of now, I see the examples, which are pretty cool. Yeah. Yeah. So my, my quote the, the quote I put on Hacker News was, this is OpenAI leveraging chat, GPT to write OpenAI op open API to extend OpenAI chat.
GPT. I'm confused, but it sounds sick, but yeah, I mean, so open api, you know, not to be confused is OpenAI is randomly the perfect spec for OpenAI to navigate because it, you know, is somewhat plain English. And then you just supply a description for model. You described a off method. So they actually provided a link to a repo where you can see some examples.
The examples are not very, not very flesh out. But you can do, like, bear off, I assume you can do whatever, whatever kind of off you like then you just provide like logo url, legal info url. It's not, it's not, it's not that much. This is 10 times better than Chrome manifest.
Like manifest v3. Yeah, I mean, I'm reading through some of these examples and a lot of them are in Python. I wish they would've more JavaScript stuff, but I would say 10 times would be kind of an understatement if I'm understanding how some of this stuff is gonna work. English is all you need, man.
English is all you need.
Well, so, so, and then I think in buried in the video is sort of the Ethan experience, right? Which is where you specify. So if you're, if you're first party congrats, you know, you're, you're inside of the the chatt ui, but if you're third party, you can just host your Js o file anywhere. It's literally a JSON file on an API spec, right?
You hosted Jason file anywhere. And then you just like plug it into their their, their text field here and then they, they validate a little bit and it's installed. So there is a third party app store on day one. Yeah, that open table plugin example is pretty sick. Yeah. So like yeah, I I What would you want as a developer that's missing?
I think that we're like in the golden age of of being a developer and I don't know if it's gonna go downhill quickly or if it's gonna go like, get better quickly or this is like the, the end of all of it. like, is OpenAI just gonna be where like we do everything like nothing else is like gonna exist.
I think that Okay. You know what I, I know that's not the answer for sure. I'm just kind of joking, but I think it will, this is obviously shut down a lot of companies. This is the app store moment, right? For like, just like, I mean, you and I remember the iPhone app store moment. Some people dropped everything to write apps and they made it big and some, a lot of people did not.
But the people who were earlier rather than later probably benefited from understanding the platform. Like imagine, imagine you, like, you know, you, you are a big React native person for a long while. Like imagine if you had the chance to drop everything and be one of the first developers on a new app store.
Like that's pretty huge. Yeah, a hundred percent. But I'm wondering like the, the type of mode that you'll be able to build with some of this stuff, because it seems like that OpenAI AI will just continue adding more and more features directly into the platform. But I think like for very like, Proprietary type of stuff.
It might make more sense, but like if you, if you want to build like an app for the general public it just seems like they'll end up integrating something like directly within their platform for a lot of different ideas like, such as this travel app that I sold. I have a feeling like they'll have a way better version of that built directly into their platform sometime soon.
Q&A: ChatGPT Waitlist and Voice
Hey, hey guys. Can I ask just to get a quick update does anyone here have access to it yet? Like is it, is it open? Cause I signed up for the wait list, but I haven't seen anything yet. Yeah, no, it's just, it's just wait list where just like 90% of the stuff that people launch, you know, she has a few, she has a few videos and demos, but yeah, it's just a wait list.
Who knows? I mean, thanks. Opening OpenAI Pretty has been pretty good about getting people off wait list, right? Like a lot of people got off the GT four API wait list, like the day after they launched. Mm-hmm. . This one, I feel like they're quite fully baked, like it's. I wouldn't be surprised if they started dropping tomorrow.
So we'll see. But like you can start developing your, your third party plugins today, because there's examples. The docs are like two paragraphs, but that's all I need really . So, so I've been, I've been working and, and I've been following a lot of projects where people are, the one thing I don't see with ChatGPT is like, why are they have, we have Whisper, we have the APIs for ChatGPT.
It's like, why are we not at the point where we're talking to this thing and it's talking back to us? Like, I don't know how we haven't, nobody's wrapped their head around that yet, but it's like, it seems to me like, don't you wanna be like, Hey computer build me an app that does X and it says okay and builds it for you and talks back to you.
Like, I just, it's like, I don't know. That'll be the first probably plugin that I try to work on, but it's just driving me a little nuts. That's all interesting. I like the voice interfaces because sometimes it gets really long, like some of the prompts get really long. They're like, I don't wanna talk that long.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. I was so, so I was doing, I was messing with the system prompt, basically get it to be like, Hey look, I'm gonna be talking to you. So keep it condensed. I think like the ideal interface would be like, for like, talking to, it would be like putting that at like the system level, but also, you know, being able to type as well as speak to it is just something that I'm, I'm trying to work on.
And I think with Plug, you know, if we could do that with plugins, I'd be huge. Cuz I know there's already a, like a Chrome extension that allows you to talk to it. Or, or I guess you could do it natively as well, but, you know, native stuff on like iPhone and Android is not too good.
LangChain with Human in the Loop
Hey, you, you mentioned that. Hi, by the way. You mentioned the hey way of, of talking to or having way the AI talking to you as a user. So just today there was a new release to of LangChain. I know it's kind of, not really the plugin, but this is the closest thing probably. And they edit a Ask Human tool.
So now the model can ask you a question if it's not sure. About something
to share. Share what? Go ahead. So, so the ask you if it's during its chain of thought, when it's not sure. To an example. Right, right. Oh, I would love that. Yeah. Probably not gonna do that. It's too confident. Yeah, I, I've seen a little bit about. LangChain, but I haven't used it yet. Has anyone here it?
Oh, it's all about it.
I did, I did. I built the LangChain on UI too. It's pretty nice. I mean, especially when it first came out, the, the trolling, it was like so rudimentary. But it's nice to be able to change things together. I think the agent part is pretty interesting. I haven't used it myself because I didn't need it.
But yeah, there's a, a very big community. See, see, light chain was very smart, right? Like they picked out the open source angle first, and then the others like dust or did the closed source angle. Now they have indirect competition with ChatGPT, but Langchain still has that. It's open source, extensible, like you own your agent.
Google vs Microsoft vs Apple
Them doing business deals with OpenAI in, in closed doors, right? Like, so pretty smart, like strategic position. All things considered.
It's a little, isn't it? It's like a little funny to me. That, you know, it's like goo because Google just came out with Bard, right. And I don't know if you guys have messed with Bard at all, but it's at least to me another wait list. Oh, okay. Yeah. I mean, to me it was a little underwhelming. I mean, I'm, I don't know if you've seen like the same, yeah, if you've seen like the screenshots going around, like it seems like, you know, someone tweeted it was like in, in guys in a boardroom or whoever's in a boardroom just being like, shit.
Like, we need to you know, we lost our first mover advantage here. But it's just kind of funny to me that like, I guess now Microsoft's gonna have like an app store, right? Like just after everything, you know, Microsoft dominated in the nineties and stuff, and then it was Apple, apple, apple. But it's just kind of funny to me that it's gonna be, I guess Microsoft now, right?
Bard feels like Bing does to Google. Totally. Yeah. A hundred percent. I agree with you a hundred percent. All the turntables, right?
Yeah. So for, for those of you who might have missed the earlier discussion the one thing that OpenAI or Microsoft will not do is integrate with your Google calendar. So, the one saving grace that Google probably has it, it probably owns your workspace, right? Like most of us have Google accounts, Gmail accounts.
When we work, we log into Gmail and Google, again, use Google Docs spreadsheets. So if Bard is smart, they will take advantage of that. And then slowly watch as everyone moves to Microsoft Office.
I think Apple should do a partnership with the OpenAI and basically Microsoft. Cause Google has huge advantage of Android. So basically having OpenAI on the, I, I mean, it would I mean having the partnership with OpenAI would make, I mean, very useful on I devices if they, I mean, Siri is really bad and if they integrate with I, I mean they've win the world I think.
So it would be huge, beneficial to Apple and basically the Microsoft also if they integrate together because Microsoft doesn't have any of the devices and most people, I, most ordinary people use the devices iPhone or phone and . So it would be huge advantage. And for the 10, basically Apple I, I'm very curious to see what Apple ships next.
You know, everyone's shipping AI stuff and then Apple was like, Hey, look at our AR glasses. . Yeah, but I mean, ar ar with, with the, with the 3D models that are, that are coming out cuz isn't it mid journeys working on like a three, like their lab, I know is, is building a 3d generative model. And I think that sort of stuff with, with AR is very, oh, is that, is that public?
How did, how did you know that? I don't know if it's public. I, I saw a tweet about it I don't know, like a week ago. It is a semi, semi open secret in San Francisco, but I, I don't know if it's public. Yeah, I think I, I saw them, it was some context of they were talking about text to video and they were like, well we're, we're doing our like 3D modeling first.
So, I mean, my assumption is, and I, I don't work in the space yet, unless anyone's hiring please, I'm looking for work. But it seems to me like Apple. Seems to have their head on straight and like it might be that if they're gonna release these ar like mixed reality ar vr glasses, like, you know, the mo the thing that makes the most sense to me is like getting with generative AI graffiti modeling.
It's like, you know, it would be cool to go to like a coffee house or a bar. And then, you know, when you see like the graffiti in the bathroom when people write sometimes funny stuff, sometimes, like the worst stuff you've ever read in your life and you're like, what is going on when this person's going to the bathroom where they have this much hate?
But it's like, it would be cool to have a component of that, you know, like in the metaverse, so to speak, right? Like, so you put on your AR glasses and it's like, oh cool, I can see like a bulletin board here that exists in the fizzled. But it's also in the, you know, it's like augmented, right? That's just, to me it seems to be like the logical next step.
Interesting. Well, we'll, we'll see that when that happens. I recently got a Quest Pro quest to my, and yeah, my parents love it. And any tech, any type that my parents like, I think has a real crossover appeal. You know, the thing that you, your conversation had gimme an idea for winners of every app store in the early days, like Facebook has an app store, apple had an app store, you know, the winners of an app, store games like what we need Yep.
Is a multi-player. Like everyone logging into chat, BT and then playing a multiplayer game line. Mpc. MPCs are gonna text you on your. , that would be kind of cool.
ChatGPT Plugin Ideas
Actually. I was thinking, I don't, I don't know if it's gonna be game games at first though. Like, it seems like games always push the envelope with tech.
Well, it's like pornography and games, right? But like, I don't know, I was talking to like, you, you mentioned your parents and like you know, I was talking to my mom about this stuff and I was like, you know, I'm seeing stuff that are just demos of just like, Hey, take a picture of your fridge and it'll tell you like, here's what you can make.
Or you know, even like talking to it and just being like, Hey, here's what I ate today. You know, what's my, how many calories I ate today? Or, you know, what's my diet plan? Just things like that. And that's why I brought up the talking to it just with na using natural language and then having it, being able to talk back to you.
I'm surpri I'm like really surprised that they haven't implemented that yet. Cuz it seems to me like that's a use case that a lot of people would use it for, you know? Or if you could just like, you know, call it on a phone if you built like a Twilio back in, into it or something. Like I just don't, it, it boggles my mind why they haven't.
Put that feature in yet? . Yeah. Yeah. I really don't think it's gonna be too long before you're, you're sitting there at work and you get a text or call on your phone from an nbc, Hey, our village is burning down. You need to come over here and help . Do, do you guys think there's gonna be different silos?
Like you know, with Bard coming out and you know, people implementing GP T three and four now, I guess, into all their apps, but do you think they'll be like, chat GP p chat, GP, PT will have their store and then Google will have their store? Do you think it'll be like, there's gonna be a clear Victor here and then, you know, it'll be like, okay, Google's apps or, you know, Google Docs or whatever is like part of chat GP t's plugins, right.
Yeah, it is gonna be like crypto. Everybody's just gonna be fighting for the top. You're gonna have the couple of dominant people, but then you're gonna have all the, the small guys who go up and down and Yeah, I I, I feel like it's gonna be pretty similar to, to how crypto was. So we're gonna have some slur juices is what you're telling me.
Yeah, boy. Nice, nice. I dig it.
Not an app store?
So may maybe we aren't, tell me what you guys think about this, cuz maybe we aren't thinking about this right? Because maybe this is not an app store. Cuz typically in an app store you'll go ahead and choose which plugins you want installed, like on a phone or whatever have you.
But the path forward seems like all the plugins are like omnipresent. I, I don't know why Google isn't shitting their, shitting their pants right now. Cuz basically you check like openly I could just force all. The big companies to write plugins and then just be a single search box for everything. So imagine if you wanna like fly somewhere or you wanna book a hotel you, we have the Expedia and booking.com.
Both of those plugins summoned up and it shows you both the results. And then you can click through on whichever ones you want. And then, yeah, you charge 'em based on click throughs. Like I, I think like we're, maybe we're just getting tripped over by the fact that you have to choose a plugin right now and only interact with that single plugin.
But I think I think the smart move forward would probably be just to have all of them omnipresent and then have this like n l p higher layer up there to summon the right plugin when need be. What, what do you guys think about that? Yeah, so, so that's like the LangChain thing. That's what I haven't used LangChain yet, but it sounds like that's, from what I was reading with LangChain, it sounds like that's kind of is how I thought that worked.
But I don't know, can someone here like enlighten me? I, I don't know if it, how, how LangChain works.
LangChain and the Future of AI
Yeah. I don't know how LangChain works either, but I think it's gonna be a two-way street. Everybody's gonna be making plug-ins with chat GP p t and everybody's gonna be making chat GP plug-ins for other services as well. I think there's gonna be a whole bunch of people about to make a bunch of Jira plugins and stuff like that, so I think it's kind of gonna be a, a two-way street.
I dunno, is anyone else, like, this is super exciting to me. I haven't been this excited about like, the internet since like, probably like the, like the web 1.0 days. Like I, I, I hate, I'm so . Yeah. Like, I hate web two. Like, this is cool. I'm glad that like spaces exist, but I hate Web 2.0, like Web 3.0. I'm about, and like, I, I consider this part of Web 3.0.
But it's exciting, right? Like, this is cool. Like I, I'm really, you know, I'm stoked about, about the progress that's being, like, the joke is like, you know, every day in, in AI is like, it's like way longer, right? It's like we're telescoping very quickly. Yeah, I mean, one of the things, telescope and updating.
Yeah. You know, I, I would say I noticed towards, maybe like three years ago when I was working at aws, it just seemed like for, for about five or or so years, everything was very stagnant and there just wasn't a lot of exciting things that were happening. Everyone was like, if you remember, all the Devrel advocates were like all creating like tutorials around creating your own CMS and your blog, and you saw like that exact same tutorial given by like hundreds of people over the course of a few years because there just wasn't any cool shit that was happening.
And then I think when crypto and, and blockchain stuff like that kind of caught my attention. Caught my attention, and I'm still excited by that, that stuff. And then this seems to be just almost like when, if you were like around when the iPhone was coming out and actually realized how important it was, I think everyone now is, is seeing this and they're all like realizing how important it is.
And it's cool to be like part of this moment as a software engineer. Yeah, I'm, yeah, go ahead. Oh, sorry. I was gonna say, like, I'm, I'm excited for you, I'm sure you guys saw the alpaca stuff, right? And I know that they're doing D D M C A stuff, but essentially someone's gonna train one of these models and it's gonna, you know, you're gonna be able to run this stuff offline.
And just like the way to, if, if you have access to like I forget which one of the EAC accelerate people was talking about it, but it was like wharf in the flask. It's like you've gotten the machine offline. So if you don't need internet access to access, like, the entirety of human knowledge, whatever's in the data set up until 2021 or whatever, and you don't need internet access, like that's gonna revolutionize everything.
Like, that's insane to think about
Yeah. Oh, well we won't speculating You can run in Inside Chat runs Python. Oh, really? Is that, is that happening? I mean, it has a file system and it has file storage and CPU at memory. Yeah.
is turtles all the way down. Turtles all the way down, man.
The, I, I think the plugin system, if people can get to run their own models like the LAMA ones and the same structure for plugins, you can see like going back to the Metaverse thing like a and snow crash where people built their own like demons. You know, it's like I got the demonn that like kicks people out of the club, the, the black sun.
But you can see in real life it's like I have a bunch of plugins that only I have, you know, and I use them to make myself more productive, use them to make myself, you know, look like I'm working when I'm not working and I'm like responding to my emails and stuff like that. But I think like, The OpenAI releasing this today makes it so much easier to start it because you don't have to worry about any of the infrastructure.
You just build the plugin and then they run everything and you get the best model possible. But I think none line, you know, I would love to walk around with my own, you know, raspberry pie or whatever of my wrist, kind of like I'm fall out and say, Hey, I wanna do this, I wanna do that. I don't know, I don't think we're that far away, so I'm excited to, to keep building.
Shoot, the, the technology exists where you could make that now, but it'd be a little awkward to have a raspberry pie on your wrist at the moment. . Well, well, well, that's kind of what I'm saying with the, with the al alpaca thing, right? It's like if you don't need internet access to, to use the model, I mean, we're, we're still pretty far off floor.
I don't know if Moore's Law even applies anymore. You know, we're not that far off from being able to run this stuff on, you know, consumer hardware that's cheap and that's gonna be huge for, for, you know, the majority of the world, right? Like, that's gonna be very big. Like e e even bigger than this. Like, it's great that we can do it with the internet, but as soon as we don't need the internet to access it, like it's, it's over, but we're back.
Whatever, whichever one you believe. It's just, this is crazy to think about that. Yeah, you could, you could if that happens, you can go and hook it up to a coding compiler and have it sped out human readable errors, but at that point it's probably just gonna be brighten on the cup for us anyways.
So we have a Hey guys. Hey. Hey, Alex. Go ahead. I, one more question, but yeah. Oh, go ahead. No, no, no. I have a right in question from someone who's trying to join but was unable to Stefani. , who I met, by the way, at the LangChain Hackathon, LangChain meetup in San Francisco. She has a lot of cool insights.
Q&A: ChatGPT Bots and Cronjobs
Follow it. Yeah, go ahead, Alex. I'll, I'll cue the question up. Oh yeah, for sure. Uh, One thing that really got my mind out this stuff and, you know, high vision mode is the fact that you can kind of externalize memories now. So the main use case I was thinking about is you could basically set up crime jobs, for lack of a better word.
So suppose you're, I don't know, building a trading bot, right? And you can say, Hey, Chad, GPT, look at the price of wheat every day at midnight. And you can just cue that up in the background and then have that send the response back to back to the LLM at a certain time. , and, you know, that's just like one use case.
But here comes like the play where like there's time sensitive things that break the one by one synchronous nature of ChatGPT and adds a little more, you can say from one level more humanness to it rather than like direct response and reply with latency. So there's that level, but also you can like schedule tasks and I think that's gonna be the killer plugin, whoever creates like the, the cal.com or the you know, theron integrations for just like, Hey, look at this point in time, and they give me the response.
I don't know if anybody's been thinking about that. Yeah, I, I was thinking about that a lot. Like how you said the expand, it's like an expandable, it's like a portable brain. Like, it's like, Hey, here's my secondary brain and it does, it's like my secretary, or it's like my assistant, right? Like somebody had a prompt where it was, you know, you're a form of, you know, one person's wisdom, one person's, you know, thinking about.
things x X way. Someone's thinking about it y way and like being able to have that just on demand with the like expandable component where you're able to basically Yeah. Delegate tasks to it and be like, Hey, you know keep what's, what's like the way to think about it? Like, not like a crime job, well, sort of like Aron job, but like like, you know, like news alerts, like Google news alerts, like things like that.
Just being able to be like, Hey, like keep, keep an eye on this thread for me while I do other things. And then if something comes up, you know, whether, you know, you just do some NLP or whatever, search for keywords you know, alert me or do whatever. And being able to do that without having to go through, you know, setting a reminder or doing all that painful, like, pain in the ass calendar stuff.
Cuz I think there's so many, there's so much software for that because people just hate doing it so much. Like, that's gonna be so big. Yeah, no, I was thinking that's probably a better way to put it, right? Like asynchronous alerts or I guess you could do timed alerts also. Because the one thing I was thinking about is the Instacart api, which is what they're demoing.
I don't know if anybody uses Instacart, but it's pretty slow on the lookups. So that's like, you know, that's a blocking process in the current integration of chat GPT. But if they could figure out a way to make it like asynchronous and then actually interact when it's done getting the, the fetch, and then you can do stuff in between that, that's gonna really change the interface.
And that's like, that's really the step closer to having like a real personal assistant in your pocket, man being able to just give chat d p t all of your Ps that you cook that week, and then just have it, order all the stuff from Instacart, from you. I can't wait for that man. Oh my God, that's great.
Oh, okay. Okay. You know, you can ship a boat Logan, like a cook, a cookbook with like actual recipe, but yeah. Yeah. Let's introduce Logan. So does this, like physical companies that integrate with software are gonna be coming like more of a moat as opposed to just software specific companies? Every software is a software company.
I know
Yeah. But if you're just a software company, OpenAI or, or, or some, one of these companies can just build that feature in now a lot easier than they could maybe in the past. Yes. For instance, you know I don't know, like we were talking about travel and, and stuff like that. But, but let's say you have a physical, you know, product that that, that maybe you can just separate yourself from other products by building, you know a better quality user experience.
Logan Joins Us!
And so we got Logan here was our first podcast guest and the first Devrel person at OpenAI actually. . So Logan, welcome. Obviously, a lot of people here are excited to talk about this. One thing I noticed from the plugins is that a lot of them are more mundane things. You know, you got travel, you got grocery.
Can you tell us a bit more about how you picked those and like maybe give us a sneak peek of other use cases that you all are excited about? Yeah, I, I think first of all, I think going back to the conversation about the ability to like queue up tasks for you in the background, I'm, my understanding is that Zapier actually already does this by default.
And I'll, I'll go play around with it after this and see, but my, I, I think Zapier has the ability to schedule things and I think this is the part. Yeah, people are sleeping on this the most is that basically Zapier is already connected.
Zapier's already connected to 5,000 different plugins, and now you can just integrate directly with all of those through Zapier, which is incredible. So you don't even need to wait for like the plugin or whatever to come. Zapier will already do that for you. Which is, which is super cool. And it already has the ability, I'm 90% sure to like schedule certain actions to happen which is awesome.
So I, I think going back to the point of like how these folks were, were specifically chosen, I think the reality was when it was initially scoped out for doing this work, there was just, we needed people who were willing to sort of deal with the idea of of sort of, we were still building this entire platform and infrastructure from the ground up.
And I think those. Those folks who were featured today during the blog post, did a lot of work of iterating on these things with us as we figured out a lot of the challenges. So huge shout out to all those, the engineering teams of those companies for, for working with us so closely to make it happen.
I just gotta say too shameless, shameless plug here. It's my birthday today and this is a super cool birthday gift. So thanks for, for doing this and the blog post. It's really awesome. happy birthday. Yeah. Thank you. Thank you. I think we all just got a, a huge gift like look like. Yeah, Logan, you don't have to speak on opening as we have here.
Like, we're all just like, you know, large model and Enjoyers here. I think. And this is a, this is a app store moment for like all of us. Like it's, I I'm just processing this and, and just trying to. Do therapy in public
There's a lot of wait list fo here, so we're all excited. Oh, yes.
Q&A: Plugins Rollout
What do we have to do to get the wait list? Yes, . I, I think the reality is yeah, it, it's, they're rolling people out really slowly and I think the intent is part of this is to understand, and I think it was one of the big highlights of the blog post about what are the new sort of accesses for, for harm here.
And I think we know some of those things, but there's a lot of known unknowns, so it'll be intentionally small for the time being. But hopefully we'll, we'll expand that access in.
bottom line, get on, get on the wait list and, and keep your, keep your fingers crossed. Come up, like come up with a cool use case. I think there's something, there's part of the wait list is like submitting what you would be interested in working on and actually in, they actually will, we will actually read that to make sure that, you know, we're bringing people in who are gonna build cool things, not stuff that's uninteresting or potentially harmful.
Okay. Are you using Tri GB two to analyze the wait list? ? Yeah, that was my question. It'll probably be humans to analyze the wait list would be my guess, but maybe, maybe not. I'm not sure. Very old. What's the difference? Old, like, yeah, yeah, we have a question from write in who couldn't join for technical issues.
Q&A: Plugins Discovery
Stefania, who is a researcher at Microsoft right now. and her question is about search. How what is the future of search for plugins? How do we discover new plug-ins? Do we need a schema for plug-ins with complex queries or, or complex behaviors? And does it limit the context window as well?
Like, do we install like a hundred different plug-ins and like, does that, does that hurt help? I don't know. . Yeah, it does. So there's a limited, and I, it's all in the developer documentation right now if you wanna read through it. But there's a bunch of limits on like your open API spec and the descriptions you use.
But we actually take all that information. We take a sample request, we take a sample response, we take the description of it, and it's actually all inside of the, the context window to begin with. So it is limited right now. And I think that's where some of those larger models like GPT four with 32 K contacts in the future, when that's the available will be super helpful and you'll be able to bring a lot of plug-ins in.
But at the current moment, the more plug-ins you add, the less, the less context to you you actually have in the conversation. Yeah, yeah, that makes sense. Makes sense. I mean with like 50 pages worth of context, that that's a lot. And you know, I was very impressed at the latency as well that that at least the demo was able to pull off, which is awesome.
Yeah. Any, any other like, reactions, thoughts, questions to plugin? I have a couple new people joining. Hey ar Yeah, I had a couple of them. If I can chime in. First of all, just blown away. I mean, it's a fairly interesting approach to deal with, like live data with this data that you guys train on. Couple of quick questions for you.
Q&A: OpenAI vs BingChat
How do you see this? Maybe it's too early to ask, but how do you see this starting out to something like a Bing Chat? The, the reason why I ask this is, I mean currently Bing is more of the UI that you're dealing with and chat GP t's being launched on the side. But do you see it more being like a platform or do you see it more consumer facing?
I mean, I dunno if this question was to me or not. Yeah, you don't, you don't have to answer that. You know, obviously Logan cannot comment on Microsoft.
I do think though, that the, the interesting differentiator is that the, the work, and I think this was in their public blog post, is that a lot of the stuff that Bing is doing is optimized for search specifically. So it's, it's just a fundamentally different experience. I still think that like if you're, if you want like that search first experience, I think something like B makes a ton of sense.
Yeah, it's just, it, it feels like a different experience to me, so, thanks.
Q&A: App Store Monetization
So I think it's been mentioned a few times that this is like the new app store or ai. What, I guess I'd, I'd like to hear thoughts of other people as well, but like, what's the, so the app store is monetized, right? So that's a big incentive for people to put their apps on there.
So how does in, in this case, you put a manifest and it hits, hits the API for your app maybe. So what side of the monetization strategy here? I mean, this is not a question for OpenAI, it's just like a general sort of direction for things. Yeah. I don't know if they care. , this is like trivial to OpenAIr.
Yeah, we were talking, you're paying for the api, right? So you're you mean like on top of, of paying for API access, like you're using your credentials, you supply your credentials when you, when you sign up to plug in. Right. So I guess you do building off platform.
Yeah, I guess so. So not from an OpenAI point of view. So Open of course, makes money on wins anyway. What I mean is like for an app developer to go on there. So I guess you have an app outside of OpenAIr, which is useful. And this is kind of distribution for your app. Is that, is that kind of the, the sale for the app?
I mean, we're three hours into it, so it's hard to say , definitely. But I think that's, I'm just waiting for someone to write a mega threat on how to make money with the app store here. Seven ways. I'm sure. I'm sure there's gonna be people on YouTube making videos with themselves streaming, and that's how they all saying, I just figure figured how, how to make millions.
But yeah, one model we were talking about was maybe you can do kind like Spotify or like a, you have Achen GD subscription and then people each plug in gets royalty. Or a lot of things. So like Instacart, like the Chan GD thing is more like a UI alternative rather than like an app itself.
So it makes a lot of sense. Do I have things like that? But yeah, it would be. . Yeah, I guess what I mean I think Dylan or somebody else said earlier that this might not be the, the app store might be like something different. I think App Store is like the closest we, we have to think about. Like that's the closest analogy, but it might be just something completely new.
And that's very interesting. I think that's that's a pretty, pretty exciting place to be. Well, well, I don't know how much overlap with like the web three stuff, but it seems to me, I know there's like a couple projects out there that are, I think there's one called Bit Tenser, where it's like people are you know, basically selling their you know, their, their GPU usage, right?
Like, you know, there's tons of gamers out there that just have, their cards are just sitting idly by, and I don't know, it seems to me like a monetization model for OpenAIr might be to, you know, they own the model, right? So it's like, I don't know if they can like, lease out the model if you could like write a smart contract that like, uses their model somehow, or, I dunno, maybe plugins could be like written into a smart contract where it's like if you, if you're using this plugin, like, I don't know how that would work specifically, but thinking ahead, like, I don't know, do you think it's gonna just be centralized this, this whole time or like, surely there's gonna be a way for this to, to spread.
And you know, obviously like there's a. What's the, what's the word? It's, it's kind of like you're trying to hold all this water back with like this one stone, and it's like eventually it's gonna break. So like, there's gonna be some decentralization in this at some point. So I don't know if that makes sense.
I'm just trying to think about like, how, how there's a monetization you know, pathway for, for this. For, for the, for these plugins.
Yeah. We're not gonna get the answer today.
Let's, it's Farmville. We're gonna, we're Farmville on ChatGPT. Let's do it. Yeah.
Q&A: ChatGPT Plugins API
. Yeah. I was interested in like if there's already an API for this or if there's like an planned, so like when chat was just a weapon interface and then we got the API later, or is this like a web only?
There is a API available today, but you have to have access to actually create plugins. So you won't have the interface to install a plugin or do anything like that. You can basically build all the stuff on the backend right now if you want to, and then when you get access you'll be able to actually install the plugin through the ChatGPT UI test it out and all that stuff.
But as of the present moment, no one beyond a very small group of people are able to actually install those developer unverified plugins. Yeah, I was I don't know if if that's what you meant, but I was thinking about like, do we have a programmatic way of calling the ChatGPT API with these plug-ins enabled and get like adjacent response back opposed to like using the weapon interface with the plug-ins enabled?
Yeah, so that, that doesn't exist yet today either. I think it's, it's unclear when and if that will come, but it's definitely something that folks are, are thinking about. I think there's just a little bit more a bunch more security and other challenges like that when you give the plugin access through the api, but it's, it's definitely something the team has talked and thought about internally.
Alright. Thanks for your insight, Leo, follow up question. Did, did you have a specific use case in mind for that that specific need that that can help to motivate things sometimes? No, not right now. It's just a general question exploring. Yeah. Well, okay. You know, you can sort of hack it together with the stuff that Diane Gross was doing in the early days of chat.
Bt. But then also, like, I, I feel like we could make like a mock validator for plugins such that we are ready to go when it's live. I don't think it'll be too hard. Yeah. Any clones, 20 clones out there for like chat ui, so you can sort to kind of hack it in. Maybe it's like not, not the highest fidelity, but the, the schema is out there, so there's nothing really stopping us apart from, you know, waking up tomorrow and, and seeing that Chad opening, I have done it already.
So , I, I think the only, the only, you could definitely do some of that today. I think some part of the challenge will be that it's a different model that's powering some of these things, which isn't available. Yeah. Yeah. I think that would be, but I still think even with probably base Sahara and just injecting some of this in there you could probably get most of the way there.
Q&A: Python Interpreter
Yeah. By the way, that, that was a misconception that I had to correct a bit early on in the space before you came on. You dropped three models today. Like there was a browsing model and then there's a separate plugins model. And the plugins model doesn't talk to the browsing model. And then there's a, you know, there's.
Python running, which is still going my mind by the way. . Yeah. The Python running also goes back to the piece around, if you wanna basically have things like set things up to dispatch, you can essentially have it write the code and just like plug into any third party library and like set up crime jobs and all that stuff for you.
So going back to sort of having chat b t do your bidding, you could, you could do all that with the code interpreter, which is super cool. And I think Greg tweeted like 20 minutes ago or an hour ago, something like that. An example of it, yes. Like doing video compression and like editing and stuff like that, which was super cool.
That that is the one. Like are we gonna have that or is that Greg's special box? Like No, I think that he's just running straight up interpreter is my understanding. I don't think there's anything special going on there because like that is insane, that like you have storage, you have compute you are a compute platform now.
Like CHATT is not a chat app. It's crazy. Like this is what made me start this space because I was like, wait, like this is not chat. This is a new thing. I don't know what this is. So yeah, I have to drop, but this was, this was awesome. Thanks for hosting this, and thanks for, thanks for having me on again.
Appreciate you. Happy birthday, Dylan. Hopefully this was a, a worthwhile present. , it was great. Thanks for coming on. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. All right. Bye, Logan. Okay. A couple more questions. If anyone has them. These things tend to drag on a little bit, so I always like to end on a well-defined note. Anyone else have reactions, questions, see anything out there that might be interesting?
I did see you know, the, the, the chat partners are starting to tweet out some stuff, so Ane Patel tweeted up about the Milo plugin that they developed with OpenAI, so we can see a little bit of that. Oh, particularly, I haven't particularly like dived in. . But yeah, you know, I, I'm collecting all, all sorts of information and, and reactions.
I'm gonna write out something today because I think this is one of the biggest days again, in tech since, I dunno, Tuesday since last week.
it's hard, but I mean, does anyone agree that things were like, really boring for a while? And this is like the first exciting thing that I've seen. The, the reacts people are still talking about use effects. Like, fuck that. Like ? Yes, exactly. Like we were stuck and reacting like CMS land for like 10 years, just.
Thank God. Thank God. Hey Peter. Hey. Thanks for having me on.
The History of App Stores and Marketplaces
I just wanted to say something real quick to the person that was asking earlier about monetization models and, and plug-ins and touch and I just, I thought one, one thing that occurred listening was that you know, a lot of these, I've done a lot of these plug-in marketplaces over my career and I think there's obviously an opportunity to like, offer different levels of validation and sort of test compatibility kit pass.
And you know, there's also an ongoing component of it cuz there's, you know, potentially data streaming through and, you know, You know, concerns around, you know, the quality of that data does it, you know, circumvent or inter interfere with OpenAI safety systems. So, you know, one obvious way that they could, you know, potentially monetize, you know, any marketplace really, you know, app store, whatever, JetBrains, you know intelligent idea marketplace, right?
Is to have that concept of different levels of validation and, and compliance, you know, to a certain specification. And, you know, you get a little logo or something like that and, you know, so anyway, just a quick thought as I was listening. Fascinating. And thanks for having me on. Hey Peter, since I want you, you to, since you had felt like you have a bunch of experience could you list like the, the, the marketplaces that you've been a part of?
And like, maybe like one thing they did well, one thing they recorded. Sure. I, I'd love to get a top down view. Sure. Yeah. I, I, I don't know that I've seen all of them, but I mean, you know, obviously I'm an iPhone and Android user, so I've, I've seen the marketplace like the rest of us. But JetBrains marketplace I think was particularly good.
Postman has a really good API marketplace rapid. I didn't know that. Rapid ap. Yeah. You know, I think, I think a lot of platform companies have gotten the message and, and they think about marketplaces, obviously the, the hyperscalers, right? You know, you've got the, you know, the, the cloud marketplaces from Amazon.
From Amazon and Google and, and Azure and such. But you know, it's some of the, sometimes it's these smaller ones that are also surprisingly good, like the intelligent idea, you know you know, you go to their website and it's like, you can buy an ad banner if you're in marketing, but, you know. Yeah. Anyway, so this concept of like validated plugins, right?
Especi. when there's this aspect of the data that's flowing through them I think presents an interesting opportunity not only for, for developers to, to make non-st plugins, pardon my frank for you know, for for OpenAI to, to, you know, say, Hey, we looked at this and not just with chat, GPT, no offense
you know, we, we we're giving it a th seal of approval. Right. You know, and that'll, that'll carry weight and carry meeting and people will pay for that is my guess. Yeah. Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Awesome. Well, if I think there's an appetite for like, understanding how to do well in the marketplace right now, if you write a post about that, I think you'll be very well received.
Sweet. Cool. I'll try to find you on Twitter. I, I just kind of dropped in. This was sort of an instinct and then I saw like, NARS here and all these other people here, so it was just kinda like, wow, this is awesome. I know, I know, I know, I know. Well, we're all just like reacting and we need a, we need a space to, to yell because this was huge.
So thanks Peter. No problem. And yeah, let's, let's connect offline.
LindyAI's Flo Crivello Joins Us
Flow is here. I'm trying to invite you, Flo. Because we were talking about Lindy earlier. We're talking about what this, what judge plugins means for Lindy. I don't think it'll, it will, I, I think actually like it will help highlight the differences.
But Oh, you're speaker. Okay. Congrats on your launch, by the way. Very, very, very well done. Thanks. Yeah. One hell of a day. . Hi everyone. Hell of a day. Did you know this was coming by the way? We didn't know it was coming today, but yes, we knew, we knew about this and we knew it would come in the, in the viewing of future.
Yeah. So I'll, I'll intro, I'll reintroduce cuz like the space is like, like four x since the time I talked about. But, you know, AI, virtual assistant is able to arbitrarily respond emails and step meetings and use natural language to do all of that. I think the, the user interface also was very, very well.
Which you know, I, I can't, I can't imagine how long you took to, to do that, but like that is the polish that you need for personal use stuff, right? Like it, this is the, this is the table six. Thank you. I'll, I'll pass your compliments to the designers who hate me now,
it did take a long time to reach this point. I mean, my take is that I think like the button is being passed from the folks like the, the, the, the lab coat researchers working on the models, they're passing the button over to like the, the product teams, basically. And I think we're gonna see a new wave of aed, not just about, Hey, we have a model that is X billion parameters, but we're gonna see a new wave of startups that own a business of building great products around these models.
And with a very simple interface, which is well, sorry, sorry. Yeah. Well, I'll tell you about plugins, but you're talking about over the foundation model APIs. . That's, that's correct. Yeah. Yeah. So I mean, are, are you worried about competition from like, you know, chatt, like, let's, let's talk, let's talk this out, right?
Like what do you see sort of the products gaps that, that PTs have versus whistle? Yeah. My understanding is that chat PT is really like chatt plugin by understanding, so up on the announcement, it's like, it's really more of like a developer product. So OpenAI is remaining true to the DNA of like, you know, we're building models and we're building stuff for, for developers to build product on.
So the impact on companies like Lin is that it's lowering the barrier to entry, which I think you're not targeting developers. Yeah, well, it's not just, it's like, it's become easier to buildy, like a whole lot of stuff that we've built, like over AI just released for free and we're like, well, fuck, like, I guess we build that.
So it's, it's lowering the barrier to entry, but you know, you, you're still left with your expertise. . Yeah, that's true. That's true. Yeah. And also also commenting before you came on that open, I probably will never have Google Calendar on their list of preferred, you know, plugins. They'll never have Gmail on.
And, and your, your integration is already super tight like this, this plugs in exactly to where, what people use today instead of having difficulty Microsoft and Google. Yeah. I wouldn't say never. I think the, but certainly their incentives are not secure aligned. And so I think there is going to be merit in being Switzerland here.
Right? It's like, look, our incentives are aligned with you as the user. Like we're not embed with, with Microsoft or Google or whatever. We're not protecting an existing ecosystem. We're just like, send AI assistant and we are gonna play as well as we can with all of your product. Yeah. Yeah. Does anyone have like I'll open up, you know, obviously we have the founder of Lindy here.
Like, does anyone have questions about Lindy? Did you see the launch? Did you have a follow up? Like this is a very nice place to. Ask it. Unless you wanna , you wanna start? I just wanna get, I'm gonna pay you just wanna get access. yesterday. It would be cool for you to maybe talk a little about how the integrations work.
And I know you're using natural language for it. I think like when tools like it, they think, oh, is my tool gonna be supportive? So yeah, maybe you wanna talk about it. Yeah, definitely. So the, and so I actually tweeted about that separately. Like, the way we build integration is we literally just give the documentation of the API to Lindy and then she out how to use the APIs on her own.
And so it's trivial for us to build a new integration. Like it actually takes 15 minutes to build a new integration. And so the answer to will my product, like, will my thing be supported will be yes. Like in 15 minutes. Like, it'll be like, Hey, you asked us do something. And literally it's like, we couldn't do it yesterday and today we can.
And it's gonna be as simple as that. So, yeah. . Yeah. I, I think to me the most interesting thing is that a lot of companies, I mean, even if you think about Airbyte and Fivetran, like when it comes to connectors, there was like the whole closed source versus open source. Like the open source usually at an advantage because the community can help you build more connectors.
But now using natural language, like the barrier is so much lower and just, it's just super exciting to, to, to use everything right away instead of waiting like four months because I'm the only person using that one tool. So excited to, to . Yeah, 100%. Well, even considering a world in which the user creates their own integration by themselves in like 10 minutes, it's like, hey, like give us, really the only thing we need is like, we need a, a documentation and then we need like an API token.
Like that's the only part that right now requires like an engineer's involvement. But you know, perhaps some power users would be fine generating some developer API token and building their own integration in like 10 minutes. I mean, I, the, the sort of app store model between Google and, and Apple and it's like the bar for quality that they held, you know what I mean?
That, that, I don't know. It's, it's, I don't know. It makes me think of that whole race again and it's like, do you lower the bar for quality and, and go the Android route or do you keep the qual, do you keep the bar high? And especially if, if there's, you know, issues with circumventing or interfering with safety systems and, and data quality and you know, things that are inappropriate, like, I dunno, I wonder, it makes me think, well the thing is that there is a ceiling to quality here when it comes to this integration.
Like, how good can you make a Gmail integration? There's like, there's like 20 endpoint or something, and then the question is like, can you call this endpoint and can you support their parameters? And it's not even the user who would actually like write the endpoint and the parameters. They would literally just like point us to the right API documentation.
Good point. . Yeah, I do think it's a little scary when I give my, you know, if I give like my, my Gmail integration and then you have Brad access, like actually just open source, the GBD four, like email drafter. And I didn't put any auto send or anything like that because I was so scared of it. But I wrote all the code, so it's I trust it.
But it'll be interesting to see how people are gonna trust these systems. Yeah. So we've built some, like hard guardrails in place where certain actions especially any endpoint that is a post endpoint we, we, we flag these actions as like, we call them like a right action. So it's like read action versus right actions.
And if it's a right action, we require user of information in a way that I mean this is like technical details, but like, it, it is physically impossible for the model to actually take a right action without user of inform. So the user, it asks for his information and like the user through the confirmation actually issues a token that is required for the model to be able to call that, that thing.
AI Safety
How worried about you about AI safety is, is this like coming from a place of UX or AI safety? , I'm, I'm super worried about very long term AI safety, right? Yeah. I am, I am, I am moderately worried about like medium term AI safety, like the whole like misinformation thing and like, yeah, like I'm sure there are ways in which Lindy may go wrong, but like, that's not the top of my concerns, and especially because I've built this kind of system.
Like I see the ways in which you can build guardrails and like, this is just like an engineering challenge. Like it's, it's very solvable now. The very long term AI safety thing, like Yeah, I mean there's like an existential race and this is, this is a whole different beast. Yeah. Part, part of me, like trying to do B2B stuff, you know, in the, in the face of AI safety issues, it feels like, you know, you're just kind of rearranging textures on the Titanic.
Or like, you, you know, you're the four piece string quartet playing music to entertain people while the strip is thinking like . Yeah, yeah. It is discouraging a little bit because you, you don't really have a take on the problem, do you? Right. You're like, all right, I guess this is coming. And I, like, I, I, I'm my head and I'm like, I don't really see what I can do about it.
Sam Altman seems to think he can turn it off. Like he has his blue bag, which presume presumably has the off the off button. That that's why he, that's why he always has it with him. Dunno. Yeah. I dunno. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, . Yeah.
Multimodal GPT4
Well, can I get your reactions just generally on like potential of like maybe multimodal GT four, like just anything that your, your, you know, US builder are looking to really take advantage of as it, as it comes down the line?
Yeah, I think multimodality and you know, audio and, and image especially, I think is like the next big zero to one thing, but otherwise, I think like, just language gets so far, man. So I was just having this conversation. To me it's the same thing as like the cpu, right? Where it's like Fairchild Semiconductor and like Intel, like they gave us the CPU and I think again, like the lab coat researchers passed the button to the hackers and Z garage, like the Steve Jobs and, and, and Steve Snak who now owns the business of building the pc.
And so that doesn't mean that like innovation in the CPU is over, like the CPU still has like four decades of ahead of it. But yeah, like we've got the cpu and now I think that the product and engineering and hacker teams have to, to take it from there. I mean, Intel did pretty well. Totally. Yeah.
I'm not, I'm not saying like OpenAI is going anywhere, for sure. Yeah. Cool, cool, cool. Uh, Any other yeah, does anyone else have questions? No, I see you unmuted.
Designing AI-safe APIs
Yeah. Just upon the on the like safety, AI safety side, I mean, as much as I Sure. Hit the complexity of Im I mean like permissions in AWS and GCP and so on, the server purpose, and I think like maybe in this page, like if you can hit any endpoint on the internet like how do you control which endpoint?
Yeah. So maybe this is, this is like a connection for flow, like one new generation of Im, which is, you know, you have a proxy sitting in front of, in front of the internet and you're only allowed to see certain parts of the internet. You said you have like, you have like right access on the post request already, but yeah, maybe there's something around.
Yeah. So we're looking into this kind of catchall guardrails right now. The way our must, for example, the Gmail API is, so it actually writes code, but at no point does it use a library to make rest API and, and phone calls, right? Like it actually we give it a function that's like Gmail, send email with like primaries for like two and subject and bugging and all of that stuff, right?
And certain of these actions, again, require an authorization token that is specific for like that one action, and these authorization tokens actually expire. So yes, in theory the model could circumnavigate that by writing code to like call the, the API endpoints directly. We've not seen it do that yet.
And, and that's just not the way we train the model to behave. That's pretty response. That's like general platform question for maybe you in the future, maybe OpenAI. That if you hook it up to the, how do you prevent it from, I, I'm not saying that the AI will do something malicious, but like a developer who gets it to write some code and hidden endpoint that you didn't give it permission for.
So for example, you can, in Deno, I I love the permission system in Deno. You can give it access to your file system or the n or you know, like the internet, but like how do you specify only a part of the internet or only a part of a domain or so on?
Yeah, so open by the way, I, I, I'm a little bit bearish on the Deno permissioning because it's permissioning on the whole executable. And and that's, you know, it's basically you're going to try to relax it the moment you run into errors and people just kind of relax it all the way, you know, it's kind of.
True. Very. I was actually I, the way I got around it, I, I was starting a new a new process subprocess and only giving it access. Really? So instead of making Yeah, it was, it was really done. Really annoying. Well done. They should go get it only. Exactly. Yeah. It's kind of overselling the security if like everybody just runs like, you know, pseudo whatever the pseudo is in, in, in Deno.
But yeah. Okay. Cool. Any other reactions?
Flo's Closing Comments
Flo, before I'll give you the, the last word here, just reactions to Chatt, PT and open the eye shipping velocity in general. You're, you're always a good speaker, so leaving to you for soundbites. Soundbites. No, it's great. You know, I, I, I'm excited to see this kind of product, see the light, and I, I, I don't use them as like direct competitors just yet.
And even if they. Look, I think the market, this is going to be the model of our market, so I think it's gonna be, it's gonna be more than fine, but maybe room full. Mini here. Blue ocean. That's right. Time to build. Let's go. What do you think swyx? What do I think? I, I, I, I don't know what to think. That's, this is why I started this space because I saw that CHE BT can run f fm Peg, which means it is a compute platform, right?
Like it generates Python code, it runs the Python code. It can receive files, it can store files, it has memory and then it can let you download the files. Give it some GPUs, and you can run Lama inside of chat, gbc, for whatever reason you want. It is a new compute platform now, and I want to build for it, but I don't know what I, what I can.
Yeah, I, I agree. I think it's, it's, these large models are like the next operating system. I'm, I'm very convinced that that's the way people are gonna interact with the computers. Like, you're no longer gonna do work at your computer, you're gonna have a conversation with your computer and the computers gonna work for you.
Well, you're, you're certainly building the platform for that. So everyone go check out Lindy. I think this is a great conversation. I always want spaces to end on a high note. But thanks for joining in. I know it's like zero notice. I was just DMing you. But thanks for coming on, man. Yeah, thanks everyone.
Yeah, all. Go out there. Bye. Thanks.