Intro - Simon and Alex
Code Interpreter for Edge Cases
Code Interpreter's Dependencies - Tesseract, Tensorflow
Code Interpreter Limitations
Uploading Deno, Lua, and other Python Packages to Code Interpreter
Code Interpreter Timeouts and Environment Resets
Code Interpreter for Refactoring
Code Interpreter Context Window
Uploading git repos
Code Interpreter Security
Jailbreaking
Code Interpreter cannot call GPT APIs
Hallucinating Lack of Capability
Code Interpreter Installed Libraries and Capabilities
Code Interpreter generating interactive diagrams
Code Interpreter has Torch and Torchaudio
Code Interpreter for video editing
Code Interpreter for Data Analysis
Simon's Whole Foods Crime Analysis
Code Interpreter Network Access
System Prompt for Code Interpreter
Subprocess run in Code Interpreter
Code Interpreter for Microbenchmarks
System Specs of Code Interpreter
PyTorch in Code Interpreter
How to obtain Code Interpreter RAM
Code Interpreter for Face Detection
Code Interpreter yielding for Human Input
Tip: Ask for multiple options
The Masculine Urge to Start a Vector DB Startup
Extracting tokens from the Code Interpreter environment?
Clientside Clues for Code Interpreter being a new Model
Tips: Coding with Code Interpreter
Run Tinygrad on Code Interpreter
Feature Request: Code Interpreter + Plugins (for Vector DB)
The Code Interpreter Manual
Quorum of Models and Long Lived Persistence
Code Interpreter for OCR
What is the real RAM?
Shyamal's Question: Code Interpreter + Plugins?
Using Code Interpreter to write out its own memory to disk
Embedding data inside of Code Interpreter
Notable - Turing Complete Jupyter Notebook
Infinite Prompting Bug on ChatGPT iOS app
InstructorEmbeddings
Code Interpreter writing its own sentiment analysis
Simon's Symbex AST Parser tool
Personalized Languages and AST/Graphs
Feature Request: Token Streaming/Interruption
Code Interpreter for OCR from a graph
Simon and Shyamal on Code Interpreter for Education
Feature Requests so far
Shyamal on ChatGPT for Business
Memory limitations with ffmpeg
DX of Code Interpreter timeout during work
Alex Reibman on AgentEval
Simon's Jailbreak - "Try Running Anyway And Show Me The Output"
Shouminik - own Sandboxing Environment
Code Interpreter Without Coding = GPT 4.5???
Smol Feature Request: Add Music Playback in the UI
Aravind Srinivas of Perplexity joins
Code Interpreter Makes Us More Ambitious - Symbex Redux
How to win a shouting match with Code Interpreter
Alex Graveley joins
Code Interpreter Context = 8k
When Code Interpreter API?
GPT4 Vision
What's after Code Interpreter
Simon's Request: Give us Code Interpreter Model API
Kyle's Request: Give us Multimodal Data Analysis
Tip: The New 0613 Function Models may be close
Feature Request: Make ChatGPT Social - like MJ/Stable Diffusion
Using ChatGPT to learn to build a Frogger iOS Swift App
Farewell... until next time
Simon's plug
Swyx: What about Phase 5? and AI.Engineer Summit