Intro
Recapping June 2023 Updates
Known Issues with Long Context
New Functions API
Riley Goodside
Simon Willison
Eric Elliott
Functions API and Agents
Functions API vs Google Vertex JSON
From English back to Code
Embedding Price Drop and Pinecone Perspective
Xenova and Huggingface Perspective
Function Selection
Designing Code Agents with Function API
Models as Routers
Prompt Engineering replaced by Finetuning
The 2 Code x LLM Paradigms
Smol Models for the future
The Evolution of the GPT API
Functions API Security vs Prompt Injection
GPT Model Upgrades
JSONformer
Closing Comments - What We Want Next